<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!--
  ~ JBoss, Home of Professional Open Source
  ~ Copyright 2005, JBoss Inc., and individual contributors as indicated
  ~ by the @authors tag. See the copyright.txt in the distribution for a
  ~ full listing of individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ This is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
  ~ under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ This software is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  ~ MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
  ~ Lesser General Public License for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
  ~ License along with this software; if not, write to the Free
  ~ Software Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
  ~ 02110-1301 USA, or see the FSF site: http://www.fsf.org.
  -->
<chapter id="packagemanager_components">
    <title>JBoss Package Manager Components</title>
    <para>
        So let's see what the JBoss Package Manager comprises of.
    </para>
    <sect1>
        <title>Package</title>
        <para>
            A "package" is nothing more than a .jar file (or a .zip file) which in-turn contains the set of files that
            are required for a particular service to be made available within the JBoss Application Server. A package
            is expected to contain a file named package.xml at the root of the package. The package.xml contains all the
            necessary information about the package which it represents. A package can contain libraries (.jar files)
            or configuration files (.xml files) or script files (.bat, .sh) or anything else. Expect for the presence of
            the "package.xml" file, a package is not restricted to contain any other files that might be required in that
            package.
        </para>
        <para>
            As we mentioned in our earlier sections, installing a package is equivalent to adding a new service to the
            application server. And since services are nothing more than a set of files, a package is expected to contain
            those set of files to be installed. These files are listed in the package.xml through the &lt;file&gt;
            element. In a later section, we will go into the details about this &lt;file&gt; element. A package can also
            specify dependencies on other packages. These dependencies are externalized from the package.xml and are
            listed in a separate file within the package. The name, structure and the location of the file listing these
            dependencies isn't restricted - except that it should be located within the package. The package.xml will
            then just point to this dependencies file through the &lt;dependencies&gt; element. This will looked in greater
            detail, in a later section.
        </para>
        <para>
            When the package manager installs/uninstalls a package, it allows the packages to do some pre-install, post-install,
            pre-uninstall, post-uninstall activities. The package manager allows the package to run scripts during either
            or all of these phases. The package.xml, through &lt;pre-install&gt;, &lt;post-install&gt;, &lt;pre-uninstall&gt; and
            &lt;post-uninstall&gt;, elements allows the package to specify such scripts.
        </para>
        <para>
            Apart from dependencies on other packages, a package might have some restriction on the systems where this
            package can be installed. For example, a package XYZ, might only work against JBoss AS-5.1.0 version. Such
            requirements can also be declared in a package.xml file through the use of &lt;system-requirements&gt; element.
        </para>
        <para>
            Now let's see each of these elements in the package.xml in detail.
            <note>
                <para>
                    The xsd for package.xml is available at http://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/jbossas/projects/ejb3/trunk/package-manager/src/main/resources/package.xsd
                </para>
            </note>
        </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>&lt;file&gt; element in the package.xml</title>
            <para>
                A &lt;file&gt; element is the minimal content that's expected in a package.xml (other than the name of
                the package and it's version). The file element declares the file within that package which has to be
                installed into the server. The file element has the following attributes:
                <informaltable frame="all">
                    <tgroup cols='4' colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colwidth='0.5in'/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Attribute Name</entry>
                                <entry>Mandatory/Optional</entry>
                                <entry>Default Value</entry>
                                <entry>Details</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>

                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>name</entry>
                                <entry>Mandatory</entry>
                                <entry></entry>
                                <entry>This is the name of the file within the package</entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>src-path</entry>
                                <entry>Optional</entry>
                                <entry></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    The value for this attribute, specifies the relative path of the file within this package.
                                    If the file is located at the root of this package, then the src-path need not be specified.
                                    If however, the file is located within a sub-folder (eg: lib) of the package, then
                                    the value for the src-path should be set to "lib".
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>dest-path</entry>
                                <entry>Mandatory</entry>
                                <entry></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    The value for this attribute, specifies the path relative to the JBoss Application Server
                                    Home directory. It mandatory to specify this value, because it's the package which
                                    knows where this file has to be installed within the application server. For example,
                                    if the file is= to be installed to JBOSS_HOME/common/lib folder, then the value of
                                    the dest-path should be set to "common/lib".
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>type</entry>
                                <entry>Optional</entry>
                                <entry></entry>
                                <entry>
                                    The value of this attribute, specifies the type of this file. Allowed values are
                                    "config", "library" and "script". This attribute is optional and is only useful
                                    if the package manager is able to handle each of these file types differently.
                                    For example, for "config" type of files, if the package manager is able to support
                                    diff/merge support, then setting this attribute makes sense.
                                    <para>
                                        In it's current form, the package manager treats all types of files in the same
                                        way and the file type does not play an role.
                                    </para>
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>

                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>

            </para>
            <para>
                A single package can have multiple files to be installed and hence the package.xml allows multiple &lt;file&gt;
                file elements. It however mandates that there be at-least one file to be installed.
            </para>
            <sect3>
                <title>Example usage of &lt;file&gt;</title>
                <para>
                    Here's an example on how you can use the file element in the package.xml:
                    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<package name="jboss-ejb3-nointerface" version="1.0.0-Alpha1">

    <!--  Package to install a dummy jar into JBOSS_AS/common/lib -->
  <file name="dummy.jar" dest-path="common/lib" />


</package>
]]>
                    </programlisting>
                </para>
                <para>
                    One more example on how you can use the file element in the package.xml:
                    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<package name="jboss-ejb3-nointerface" version="1.0.0-Alpha1">

    <!--  Package to install a dummy jar into JBOSS_AS/common/lib -->
  <file name="dummy.jar" dest-path="common/lib" />

  <!--  Package to install a another jar into JBOSS_AS/server/default/deployers -->
  <file name="mydeployer.jar" src-path="deployers" dest-path="server/default/deployers" />


</package>
]]>
                    </programlisting>
                </para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>&lt;pre-install&gt;, &lt;post-install&gt; and other similar scripts</title>
            <para>
                A package can contain scripts which could be configured to run during the pre-install, post-install,
                pre-uninstall and/or post-uninstall phases of a package installation/un-installation. The package.xml
                allows for &lt;pre-install&gt;, &lt;post-install&gt;, &lt;pre-uninstall&gt; and &lt;post-uninstall&gt;
                elements. Each of these elements can contain one or more &lt;script&gt; elements.
                By default, a script file is an Ant build file containing some pre-defined targets. However, the
                script element allows for any other script types to be used. The script element allows the "processor"
                attribute to be set to a class which implements the org.jboss.ejb3.packagemanager.script.ScriptProcessor
                interface. It's then upto that script processor implementation to process the script file. A pre-install,
                post-install element can have multiple script and each script can be of a different type and can be
                processed by different script processor implementations.
            </para>
            <para>
                By default, the JBoss Package Manager uses org.jboss.ejb3.packagemanager.script.impl.AntScriptProcessor
                which is capable of processing Ant build files. The Ant build file is expected to contain certain pre-defined
                targets. The targets that are mandated in the Ant build script file, depend on the context in which the
                script file is run. For example, if the script has to be run during the pre-install phase of the installation
                of the package, then the file is expected to contain a target named "pre-install". Here's the entire
                set of expected targets and the context when they are expected:
                <informaltable frame="all">
                    <tgroup cols='2' colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colwidth='0.5in'/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Target Name</entry>
                                <entry>Context</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>

                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>pre-install</entry>
                                <entry>This target is expected to be present in the Ant script, if the
                                script is configured to run during the pre-install phase of the package
                                installation.
                                </entry>
                                
                            </row>
                        </tbody>

                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>post-install</entry>
                                <entry>This target is expected to be present in the Ant script, if the
                                script is configured to run during the post-install phase of the package
                                installation.
                                </entry>

                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>pre-uninstall</entry>
                                <entry>This target is expected to be present in the Ant script, if the
                                script is configured to run during the pre-uninstall phase of the package
                                installation.
                                </entry>

                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>post-uninstall</entry>
                                <entry>This target is expected to be present in the Ant script, if the
                                script is configured to run during the post-uninstall phase of the package
                                installation.
                                </entry>

                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
            </para>
            <para>
                A single Ant script file can be used for the various package installation phases, provided it
                has the required targets in that single Ant build file. Furthermore, the JBoss Package Manager
                guarantees that the following two Ant properties will be set by the package manager so that they can
                be referenced within the build scripts:
                <itemizedlist mark="opencircle">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            JBOSS_HOME - This property will point to the JBoss Application Server home folder against
                            which this package manager is processing this package.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            PM_HOME - This property will point to the JBoss Package Manager home folder.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
                The &lt;script&gt; element allows the following attributes:
                <informaltable frame="all">
                    <tgroup cols='4' colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colwidth='0.5in'/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Attribute Name</entry>
                                <entry>Mandatory/Optional</entry>
                                <entry>Default Value</entry>
                                <entry>Details</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>

                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>script</entry>
                                <entry>Mandatory</entry>
                                <entry></entry>
                                <entry>The value of this attribute, is the relative path to the script file (including
                                the name of the file), within the package. The path is relative to the location of
                                package.xml. For example, if the script file is named build.xml and is located at the root
                                of the package (i.e. at the same level as package.xml), then the value of this attribute
                                    should be set to "build.xml".
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>processor</entry>
                                <entry>Optional</entry>
                                <entry>org.jboss.ejb3.packagemanager.script.impl.AntScriptProcessor</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    The value for this attribute, specifies the fully qualified class name of the class
                                    which implements the org.jboss.ejb3.packagemanager.script.ScriptProcessor. The
                                    implementation class will then be allowed to process this script file. 
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
                
            </para>

            <sect3>
                <title>Example usage of the &lt;pre-install&gt;, &lt;post-install&gt;</title>
                <para>
                    Following is an example usage of the pre-install, post-install scripts:
                    <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
<package name="jboss-ejb3-nointerface" version="1.0.0-Alpha1">

    <!--  Package to install a dummy jar into JBOSS_AS/server/default/deploy -->
  <file name="dummy.jar" dest-path="server/default/deploy" type="library"/>

    <!-- A couple of pre-install files for this package -->
  <pre-install>
    <!-- The default Ant script processor is used for this script -->
    <script file="build.xml"/>
    <!-- A custom script processor org.somepackage.DotShScriptProcessor
    will be used to process the other.sh file which is located in the bin
    sub-folder within the package
    -->
    <script file="bin/other.sh" processor="org.somepackage.DotShScriptProcessor"/>
  </pre-install>

    <!-- A post-install script -->
  <post-install>
    <!-- We use the same build.xml file that was used for pre-install,
    because that build.xml can contain both pre-install and post-install
    targets -->
    <script file="build.xml"/>
  </post-install>


</package>
]]>
                    </programlisting>

                    
                </para>
            </sect3>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>&lt;system-requirements&gt; element</title>
            <para>
                The &lt;system-requirements&gt; element in the package.xml allows the package to specify it's requirements.
                This element currently just a place-holder. We have to think more about this, specifically what
                kind of requirements the package is allowed to specify and how is the package manager going to check
                whether the system where the package is being installed, satisfies those requirements. At the minimal,
                probably the version of the JBoss Application Server can act as the system requirement. But again, that
                would require some kind of non-trivial interaction with the application server to check the requirements.
                Overall, this needs a bit more thinking. This section will be updated appropriately once we have decided
                upon something.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>&lt;dependencies&gt; element</title>
            <para>
                As we have already mentioned various times in the document, a package usually has dependencies on other
                packages. The &lt;dependencies&gt; element in the package.xml allows the package to point to a file
                within the package which lists those dependencies.
            </para>
            <para>
                The package.xml intentionally lets the dependencies to be specified in a separate file within the package,
                whose location and format is not restricted. This allows for the various different ways in which the
                dependencies can be listed and processed.
            </para>
            <para>
                By default, the JBoss Package Manager expects the dependencies (if any) to be specified in a xml file
                which is an Ivy dependency file. For any other type of dependencies file, the &lt;dependencies&gt;
                element allows, through it's "manager" attribute to specify the fully qualified class name of the class
                which implements the org.jboss.ejb3.packagemanager.dependency.DependencyManager interface.
                This implementation of the "manager" will then be responsible for parsing and processing the
                dependencies listed in the dependency file. By default, JBoss Package Manager uses the
                org.jboss.ejb3.packagemanager.dependency.IvyDependencyManager for processing the dependency file.
            </para>
            <para>
                A single package can have only one dependencies file, and hence only one dependency manager implementation,
                listing all the dependencies in that single file.
            </para>
            <para>
                TODO: More thinking and PoC has to be done around this and this section will be updated in the next
                few days with more details and specific examples. Right now, this is work-in-progress (well, the entire
                document is actually work-in-progress :-) )
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1>
        <title>Package Build tool</title>
        <para>
            As we have seen so far, an package is nothing more than a .jar/.zip file. Expect for the presence of the
            package.xml in the package, the JBoss Package Manager does not add any other requirements/restrictions on
            the package format or contents. As such, i personally, don't see any need for an new build tool which allows
            to create the packages. Already existing tools (there are lots) like Ant build script or anything else
            can always be used to create these packages.
        </para>
        <para>
            But, if at some point of time, the requirement for such a build tool arises, then we will update this section
            with the details.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Package Manager</title>
        <para>
            Now that we have seen what a package contains and how to create a package, let's now see some details
            around the JBoss Package Manager which processes these packages.
        </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Running the Package Manager</title>
            <para>
                Note that we currently don't have a script for the package manager. Until then, you can use the
                org.jboss.ejb3.packagemanager.impl.DefaultPackageManagerImpl class and pass it the appropriate command
                line arguments. This class has the "main" method which acts as an entry point for the package manager.
                In it's current form, the JBoss Package Manager can handle the following options:
                <informaltable frame="all">
                    <tgroup cols='2' colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                        <colspec colwidth='0.5in'/>
                        <thead>
                            <row>
                                <entry>Option</entry>
                                <entry>Description</entry>
                            </row>
                        </thead>

                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>-i</entry>
                                <entry>The -i option can be used to install a package.
                                    When the -i option is used, it expects the path to the package to be specified too.
                                    See later section on what the valid values for path are.
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>-p</entry>
                                <entry>This option right now is mandatory and it points to
                                    the JBoss Package Manager home folder. The JBoss Package Manager folder can be
                                    any folder on the file system. The package manager will use this as it working
                                    environment and create, extract any of the files it needs to, while processing
                                    packages.
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                        <tbody>
                            <row>
                                <entry>-s</entry>
                                <entry>
                                    This option is mandatory and it points to home folder of JBoss Application Server,
                                    to which this package manager is installing packages.
                                </entry>
                            </row>
                        </tbody>
                    </tgroup>
                </informaltable>
                <note>
                    <para>
                        None of these options have been finalized yet. This section will be updated appropriately when
                        the final set of options is decided.
                    </para>
                </note>
            </para>
            
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Installing a Package</title>
            <para>
                To install a package you can pass the -i &lt;packagepath&gt; arguments to the package manager script.
            </para>
            <para>
                The -i argument to the package manager is to let the package manager install a package. The -i argument
                expects the path to the package manager to be specified. In it's current form, the JBoss Package Manager
                can handle file:// protocol and http:// protocols. So the JBoss Package Manager, in it's current
                form is able to work on package available either on the file system or through an HTTP URL.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Removing a Package</title>
            <para>
                This is still work-in-progress. Details will be added soon.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Updating a Package</title>
            <para>
                This is still work-in-progress. Details will be added soon.
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
</chapter>

