<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!--
  ~ JBoss, Home of Professional Open Source
  ~ Copyright 2005, JBoss Inc., and individual contributors as indicated
  ~ by the @authors tag. See the copyright.txt in the distribution for a
  ~ full listing of individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ This is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
  ~ under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ This software is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  ~ MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
  ~ Lesser General Public License for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
  ~ License along with this software; if not, write to the Free
  ~ Software Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
  ~ 02110-1301 USA, or see the FSF site: http://www.fsf.org.
  -->
<chapter id="packagemanager_db">
    <title>JBoss Package Manager Database</title>
    <para>
        In order to keep track of the packages that have been installed in the system (i.e. JBoss Application Server), the
        package manager maintains a database.
    </para>
    <sect1>
        <title>Implementation Details</title>
        <para>
            This section provides a brief overview of the implementation details about the package manager database. Normal
            users of the package manager may skip this section. But if you are interested in knowing some of the implementation
            details, then read on!
        </para>
        <sect2>
            <title>Database server</title>
            <para>
                The default implementation of the package manager uses Derby Embedded database. Derby Embedded database allows
                for the database to created and managed from within another Java application. One of the goals of the package manager
                is to reduce the additional software installations, for using the package manager. Derby fits in, because it
                does not require the DB server to be installed or started externally.
                <note>
                    <para>
                        At this point, there's no way to configure a different DB server to be used with the JBoss Package Manager.
                        There are no immediate plans to allow this either. But if in future, this feature is required, then
                        it should be easy enough to provide it.
                    </para>
                </note>
            </para>
            <para>
                Furthermore, the package manager implementation uses JPA (Java Persistence API) for it's interaction with the
                database.
            </para>
            
        </sect2>

        <sect2>
            <title>Schema</title>
            <para>
                <note>
                    <para>
                        TODO: This section will be updated soon, with the schema diagram. 
                    </para>
                </note>
            </para>
        </sect2>

    </sect1>
</chapter>
