<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!--
  ~ JBoss, Home of Professional Open Source
  ~ Copyright 2005, JBoss Inc., and individual contributors as indicated
  ~ by the @authors tag. See the copyright.txt in the distribution for a
  ~ full listing of individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ This is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
  ~ under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ This software is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  ~ MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
  ~ Lesser General Public License for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
  ~ License along with this software; if not, write to the Free
  ~ Software Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
  ~ 02110-1301 USA, or see the FSF site: http://www.fsf.org.
  -->
<sect1>
    <title>Package Manager</title>
    <para>
        Now that we have seen what a package contains and how to create a package, let's now see some details
        around the JBoss Package Manager which processes these packages.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="package-manager-setup">
        <title>Setting up the Package Manager</title>
        <para>
            The package manager needs to be setup once, before it can be used. The package manager installation contains
            the setup.sh (setup.bat for Windows OS) in the bin folder. Run the setup.sh script as follows:
           <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
[jpai@jaikiran packagemanager]$ cd bin
[jpai@jaikiran bin]$ ./setup.sh -s /path/to/jboss -p /path/to/packagemanager_home

        ]]>
            </programlisting>
            The setup.sh, through the -s option accepts the path to your JBoss server installation. It also
        requires the path to where you want the package manager to be installed. You can pass the path through the -p option.
            <note>
                <para>
                    TODO: Ideally, the setup.sh script should not require the JBOSS_HOME or the PACKAGE_MANAGER_HOME
                    options to be passed to it, for the following reasons:
                    <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                The setup.sh is meant to setup the package manager and a single installation of package
                                manager is capable of managing multiple JBoss server installations, so the JBOSS_HOME
                                param for setup script, makes no sense
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                            <para>
                                The PACKAGE_MANAGER_HOME param to the setup.sh too doesn't make sense, because it's no
                                use specifying a different home, than the current directory which contains all the package
                                manager required artifacts (like scripts, libraries etc...). The setup.sh should infer
                                the parent folder of the "bin" folder as the package manager home.
                            </para>
                        </listitem>
                        
                    </itemizedlist>
                </para>
            </note>
        </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
        <title>Running the Package Manager</title>
        <para>
            Once the package manager has been setup, you can use the run.sh (run.bat for Windows OS) script to run the
            package manager. This script is available in the bin folder of the package manager installation
            In it's current form, the JBoss Package Manager can handle the following options:
            <informaltable frame="all">
                <tgroup cols='2' colsep="1" rowsep="1">
                    <colspec colwidth='0.5in'/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry>Option</entry>
                            <entry>Description</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>

                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>-i</entry>
                            <entry>The -i option can be used to install a package.
                                When the -i option is used, it expects the path to the package to be specified too.
                                See later section on what the valid values for path are.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>-u</entry>
                            <entry>The -u option can be used to upgrade a package.
                                When the -u option is used, it expects the path to the package to be specified too.
                                See later section on what the valid values for path are.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>-r</entry>
                            <entry>The -r option can be used to remove/uninstall a package.
                                When the -r option is used, it expects the name of the already installed package to
                                be specified.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>-p</entry>
                            <entry>This option right now is mandatory and it points to
                                the JBoss Package Manager home folder. The JBoss Package Manager folder can be
                                any folder on the file system. The package manager will use this as it working
                                environment and create, extract any of the files it needs to, while processing
                                packages.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>-s</entry>
                            <entry>
                                This option is mandatory and it points to home folder of JBoss Application Server,
                                to which this package manager is installing packages.
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
            <note>
                <para>
                    None of these options have been finalized yet. This section will be updated appropriately when
                    the final set of options is decided.
                </para>
            </note>
        </para>

    </sect2>
    <sect2>
        <title>Installing a Package</title>
        <para>
            To install a package you can pass the -i &lt;packagepath&gt; arguments to the package manager script.
        </para>
        <para>
            The -i argument to the package manager is to let the package manager install a package. The -i argument
            expects the path to the package. In it's current form, the JBoss Package Manager
            can handle file:// protocol and http:// protocols. So the JBoss Package Manager, in it's current
            form is able to work on package available either on the file system or through an HTTP URL.
        </para>
        <para>
            If a package with the same package name is already installed in the system, then this new installation
            will not be allowed. The package manager will throw an error indicating the presence of an already
            installed package with the same name. In situations like this, you might want to consider using the
            upgrade option of the package manager. The details of upgrading a package will be discussed in later
            sections.
        </para>
        <sect3>
            <title>Examples of installing a package</title>
            <para>
                The following example shows how to install a package available at /home/me/packages/simple-package.jar
                into a JBoss installation available at /home/me/jboss/jboss-5.1.0.GA
                <programlisting>
 <![CDATA[
 [jpai@jaikiran packagemanager]$ cd bin
 [jpai@jaikiran bin]$ ./run.sh -s /home/me/jboss/jboss-5.1.0.GA -i /home/me/packages/simple-package.jar

         ]]>
                </programlisting>                
            </para>
            <para>
                This next one shows how to install a package available as a HTTP resource at
                http://snapshots.jboss.org/maven2/org/jboss/ejb3/tmp/simple-package.jar into the JBoss server available
                at /home/me/jboss/jboss-5.1.0.GA
                <programlisting>
 <![CDATA[
 [jpai@jaikiran packagemanager]$ cd bin
 [jpai@jaikiran bin]$ ./run.sh -s /home/me/jboss/jboss-5.1.0.GA -i http://snapshots.jboss.org/maven2/org/jboss/ejb3/tmp/simple-package.jar

         ]]>
                </programlisting>
                
            </para>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
        <title>Removing a Package</title>
        <para>
            An already installed package can be removed by using the -r argument to the package manager. The -r option
            should be followed by the name of the package which is already installed. The package manager will look
            for the installed package by this name and if not found, will throw back an error. If the package with
            this name is found to be installed, the package will be removed.
        </para>
        <para>
            Removing a package from a system, includes the process of removing any files that were installed during
            the installation of the package. Any pre/post uninstall scripts, corresponding to this package being removed,
            will also be run.
            <important>
                <para>
                    Uninstalling a package will NOT uninstall the dependencies. For example, if a package ABC was
                    installed along with its dependency packages XYZ and PQR, then during the uninstallation of
                    package ABC, neither XYZ nor PQR will be uninstalled.
                </para>
            </important>
            <note>

                <para>
                    TODO: How and where do we keep the pre/post uninstall scripts? Because during uninstall, we will
                    not have access to the original package contents.
                </para>
            </note>
        </para>
        <para>
            Also note that, if there are other packages which are dependent on the package ABC being uninstalled,
            then such package ABC will not be uninstalled.
        </para>
        <sect3>
            <title>Examples of removing a package</title>
            <para>
                The following example shows how to remove a package named "ejb3-core", which has already been installed
                in JBoss located at /home/me/jboss/jboss-5.1.0.GA.
                <programlisting>
 <![CDATA[
 [jpai@jaikiran packagemanager]$ cd bin
 [jpai@jaikiran bin]$ ./run.sh -s /home/me/jboss/jboss-5.1.0.GA -r ejb3-core

         ]]>
                </programlisting>

            </para>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
        <title>Upgrading a Package</title>
        <para>
            Upgrading a package, internally is equivalent to uninstalling and then installing the new version of the package.
            If the package was not already installed, then the uninstallation part is skipped. So the upgrade option can be
            safely used for installing new packages too.
        </para>
        <para>
            To upgrade a package you can pass the -u &lt;packagepath&gt; arguments to the package manager script.
        </para>
        <para>
            The -u argument expects the path to package. The values for the -u options are the same as that for the -i option.
        </para>
        <sect3>
            <title>Examples of updating a package</title>
            <para>
                The following example shows how to update a package available /home/me/packages/simple-package-new-version.jar
                into a JBoss installation available at /home/me/jboss/jboss-5.1.0.GA. If the package was already installed,
                then it is internally uninstalled and this new version is installed.
                <programlisting>
 <![CDATA[
 [jpai@jaikiran packagemanager]$ cd bin
 [jpai@jaikiran bin]$ ./run.sh -s /home/me/jboss/jboss-5.1.0.GA -u /home/me/packages/simple-package-new-version.jar

         ]]>
                </programlisting>

            </para>
        </sect3>
    </sect2>
</sect1>
