<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!--
  ~ JBoss, Home of Professional Open Source
  ~ Copyright 2005, JBoss Inc., and individual contributors as indicated
  ~ by the @authors tag. See the copyright.txt in the distribution for a
  ~ full listing of individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ This is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
  ~ under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ This software is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  ~ MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
  ~ Lesser General Public License for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
  ~ License along with this software; if not, write to the Free
  ~ Software Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
  ~ 02110-1301 USA, or see the FSF site: http://www.fsf.org.
  -->
<chapter id="status">
    <title>Current status</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>What's the current state of JBoss Package Manager?</title>
        <para>
            There's still lots to be done in the JBoss Package Manager. The current state of JBoss Package Manager
            has the very basic implementation of installing a package. It's currently in a PoC state and more
            functionality is being worked on.
        </para>
        <para>
            Some of features/functionalities that need to be thought about, but not limited to, are:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Diff/Merging of configuration files and maybe checksum comparisons on files being installed
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Enough of these docs, i need some action!</title>
        <para>
            In the next few days, i'll add a simple script which can be used to run the package manager. But right now,
            you can try out the org.jboss.ejb3.packagemanager.impl.DefaultPackageManagerImpl.main(Stringp[] args)
            method by passing it the appropriate arguments, listed in the previous sections.
        </para>
        <para>
            You can also have a look at the org.jboss.ejb3.packagemanager.test.install.unit.BasicInstallTestCase to
            see how the install works. That test case has been written with many comments to make sure that each step
            is explained clearly. It covers almost all of the currently implemented functionality in the JBoss Package
            Manager, including HTTP URL support. You can add your own tests there to try out the JBoss Package Manager.
         </para>
         <para>
             Now that the basic dependency management has been implemented, tests have been added to illustrate the usage
             and the functionality. The test is named org.jboss.ejb3.packagemanager.test.dependency.unit.DependencyInstallTestCase.
         </para>
         <para>
             For tests around remove/uninstall functionality, have a look at org.jboss.ejb3.packagemanager.test.uninstall.unit.UnInstallTestCase.
         </para>
         <para>
             To run the tests, use the following Maven command on the package-manager project root:
            <programlisting>
<![CDATA[
mvn clean test
]]>
            </programlisting>
            
        </para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
